Today's דף daf is ח', chet, but we are behind. We start
on the bottom of ח' עמוד א'. chet amud aleph.
And yes, unfortunately.
Okay. גופא, Gufa, five lines from the bottom, and we are dealing,
the major theme here is how the כלי שרת klei shares work.
And the question that we're dealing with now is whether they can
sanctify the מנחה mincha if it doesn't have all the ingredients present.
So let's take a look. גופא. Gufa. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so
רב Rav says, מנחה קדושה בלא שמן. mincha kedusha belo shemen. It
will be sanctified even before you've put the oil in it. You
just put the flour in the כלי שרת, kli shares, it will
become sanctified. שכן מצינו בלחם הפנים, Shekein matzinu belachem hapanim, because by
the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, that's a מנחה mincha without oil, and
the כלי שרת klei shares work to sanctify it. בלא לבונה, Belo
levona, without לבונה, levona, שכן מצינו במנחת נסכים, shekein matzinu beminchat nesachim,
because by the מנחה mincha that comes with קרבנות, korbanos, there's no
לבונה, levona, and the כלי שרת klei shares work for them. בלא
שמן ובלא לבונה, Belo shemen ubelo levona, even without oil and without
the frankincense, שכן מצינו במנחת חוטא, shekein matzinu beminchat chote, because the
מנחה mincha of a sinner comes without both, and the כלי שרת
klei shares work for them. Okay now again, this is a little
bizarre because obviously you're comparing something that that's the way it's done
to something that it's not the way it's done. And maybe in
these cases we should say, since it's not complete, the כלי שרת
klei shares doesn't work for it. But nevertheless, this is what the
גמרא Gemara phrased before as you learn out מילתא ממילתא, milta mimilta,
that you're prepared to compare things even if they're not exactly the
same to learn out some general principle. And again, because we're talking
about how כלי שרת klei shares function and the קדושה kedusha of
כלי שרת, klei shares, it's a little bit easier to make these
comparisons because we're not questioning whether the מנחה mincha is valid and
have you done the מצוה, mitzvah, but we're asking whether the כלי
שרת klei shares will operate under these circumstances.
Yes, fair enough, I'm going to say the same thing, that you
know, but it's still not valid and like, you know, and then
you still have to bring the שמן shemen and... Yeah, of course,
we're just
talking that it's already קדוש. kadosh.
And if you didn't, then I guess what you would just have
to burn it, right?
Well, your מנחה mincha would be פסול. pasul. Right. Yeah, you'd have
to burn it. Right. But at this stage, the right, at this
stage the flour is already קדוש. kadosh. Okay? One of the relevances
for the flour being קדוש kadosh is a חומרא. chumra. It means
that if it becomes טמא tamei or something, you can't redeem it
and you you know you can't redeem it. It already has intrinsic
קדושה. kedusha. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, now that's about the flour of a מנחה. mincha. How about
the other components by themselves? Okay, so it says,
ושמן ולבונה קדשי האי בלא האי והאי בלא האי. veshemen ulevona kadshi
hai belo hai vehai belo hai. And not only that, the שמן
shemen and the לבונה, levona, the oil and the frankincense, each one
can be sanctified purely independently even though they're ingredients for the מנחה
mincha when you put them in the
כלי שרת. kli shares. שמן שכן מצינו בלוג שמן של מצורע, Shemen
shekein matzinu belog shemen shel metzora, when you bring the לוג log
of oil for the מצורע, metzora, which is an independent thing that
you put on the ears and the thumbs and whatever, so that
goes into a כלי שרת. kli shares. So you see a כלי
שרת kli shares works for oil by itself. So it'll also work
for oil when it's one of the ingredients of the מנחה. mincha.
ולבונה, Ulevona, frankincense, שכן מצינו בלבונה הבאה בבזיכין. shekein matzinu belevona habaa
bevezikin. The frankincense that goes in the little spoons that are around
the שולחן shulchan with the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, they are sanctified
by themselves. So the same way these things are sanctified by themselves
when they are when they are the whole thing that is brought,
what we learn from this is that the כלי שרת kli shares
can sanctify them even when they are only one of the ingredients
of the קרבן. korban. So that's what רב Rav says. ורבי חנינא
אמר, Verabbi Chanina amar, and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says now on
ח' עמוד ב', chet amud beis, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, לא
זו קדשה בלא זו ולא זו קדשה בלא זו. lo zu kadesha
belo zu velo zu kadesha belo zu. What, no, you cannot have
them be separate
ingredients sanctified. Right. You have to have all of the ingredients of
the מנחה mincha in the כלי kli in order for it to
be sanctified, which is, let's face it, a reasonable position. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, ורבי חנינא עשרון למה נמשח. Verabbi Chanina
issaron lama nimshach. So now we have a question because we're going
to find out, like I said, a lot of מנחות menachos you
get to discuss how the כלי שרת klei shares operate. So we're
going to find out that they had these different measures in the
מקדש, Mikdash, and one of the measures was an עשרון, issaron, a
tenth of an איפה, eifah, and that עשרון issaron was the minimum
amount the flour for a מנחה. mincha. Most מנחות menachos were an
עשרון. issaron. So now that's fine, you need measuring cups, but it
was not just a measuring cup. It was anointed, it was turned
into a כלי שרת. kli shares. So the question is what...
Do we know how much that is?
I can give you a rough estimate in a minute. Let me
finish this point, okay?
Yeah because it's like five times the size...
yeah, yeah, I'll look at one of these handbooks, okay, I don't
remember offhand.
Now, what was I going to say? Ah, so the question is
not why did you need a measuring cup? The question is why
turn it into a כלי שרת? kli shares? Why anoint it with
the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha to turn it into a כלי שרת?
kli shares? Right? The only reason you would is because sometimes you're
going to put something in it that will be sanctified at that
moment. But if the מנחה mincha is flour and oil, and the
flour amount is an עשרון, issaron, then and it doesn't become קדוש
kadosh according to רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina until all the ingredients are
there. Right, you're never going to need a כלי שרת Kli Shares
for a מנחה, Mincha, you're never going to need an עשרון Isaron
for a כלי שרת Kli Shares because the מנחה Mincha will always
be larger than an עשרון. Isaron. Right? Was that clear?
What about a מנחת חוטא? Minchas Chotei? You don't have oil.
Ah, so very good, Michael.
Of course you always figure out the answer.
Okay, yeah, I'm gonna hear I got it I got the chart.
Boy, look it up, I think it's even more basic than that
because you don't want someone like you know yeah עשרון, Isaron, one
minute, one minute. An עשרון Isaron is roughly 2.49
liters.
How big is that?
2.49.
Like a bottle of Coke is two liters. Okay. So it's so
it's a you know a little bit bigger than one of those
large bottles of Coke. That's a good amount of flour. That's a
lot. That's a good amount of flour. Yeah.
Volume is always tough to visualize.
It's a volume measurement.
Yeah, volume measurement.
Liters is a volume measurement. It's for liquids.
What?
I don't understand. If it's a volume measurement it doesn't matter what
you're
putting in it.
Because it's I guess if you put if you take a two
liter bottle of Coke and you put flour in it, now you
have two liters as long as it's not weight, as long as
it's volume it can measure liquids or solids, can't it?
But they have different weight even if they have the same volume.
I know, because it's not a weight measurement, it's a volume measurement.
Right. Okay,
that still is a lot of flour.
What? That is a lot of flour. Yeah. But even even more
basically though, you know, you don't want like you want to make
like use in the process of a קרבן. Korban.
You want like you know it's
like
okay, but it wouldn't be necessary.
It wouldn't be
necessary.
Okay, fine. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. But also you
don't want
people like you know it wouldn't
be necessary you don't want someone like thinking they can go take
it home and then use it for like you know. And you
don't want them stealing things anyway. Right, that's my point. You make
it a כלי שרת, Kli Shares, now now the stakes are high.
All right, could be. Anyways, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
ורבי חנינא עשרון למה נמשח, Verabi Chanina Isaron lama nimshach, why was
it anointed? Presumable because you never needed it as a כלי שרת
Kli Shares presumably because the sanctification only happens with the oil, which
is larger than an עשרון. Isaron. So the גמרא Gemara says למנחת
חוטא, Leminchas Chotei, like Michael said, for the מנחה Mincha of a
sinner, which does not have oil, and that is exactly an עשרון.
Isaron. הלוג למה נמשח, Halog lama nimshach, why do you have to
sanctify the לוג? Log?
That's obvious. Since the right exactly exactly since the oil is always
sanctified only after it's mixed with the flour. So the answer is
ללוג של מצורע Lelog shel Metzora because there is one time that
you have a לוג Log that is sanctified by itself and that's
the לוג Log of oil of the מצורע. Metzora. Do you want
to know how much a לוג Log is while we're at it?
Sure. And why and while I've got the book here,
a לוג Log is .6 liters. So it's like half of one
of those thin bottles of soda.
I thought an עשרון Isaron was the smaller measure.
No.
No, you're mixing the oil with the with the flour. You're mixing
the oil with the לוג Log that amount of oil with the
עשרון Isaron of flour.
It's like it's basically like a five to one ratio. Does that
make sense? Yeah. Okay, great. All right.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואף שמואל סבר לה להא
דרב, Veaf Shmuel savar la leha deRav,
even שמואל Shmuel holds of רב Rav that the כלי שרת Klei
Shares sanctify the flour by itself. דתנן Detnan because we taught in
the משנה, Mishna, כלי הלח מקדשין את הלח ומדות היבש מקדשות את
היבש. Klei halach mekadeshin es halach umiddos hayavesh mekadeshos es hayavesh.
Liquid vessels sanctify liquid, dry vessels or dry vessels, vessels used
for like things like flour, sanctify sanctify dry foods. Okay, so if
you put liquid food, liquid into dry or dry into liquid, since
it doesn't belong there, it doesn't sanctify. ואין כלי הלח מקדשין את
היבש ולא מדות היבש מקדשות את הלח. Veein Klei halach mekadeshin es
hayavesh velo middos hayavesh mekadeshos es halach. So vessels made for liquids
don't sanctify dry foods and vessels made for dry foods don't sanctify
liquids. ואמר שמואל, Veamar Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel said, לא שנו אלא
מדות. Lo shanu ella middos.
That's only true with these measuring vessels. אבל מזרקות, Aval mizrakos, but
the like the the bowls used for throwing the blood that are
not used for measuring, those מקדשות את היבש mekadeshos es hayavesh would
sanctify the dry. So he says like this. Sort of like you
were sort of asking about the liter, certain vessels are made for
measuring liquids, you don't use the same vessels for measuring dry. So
there, there's really a distinction between dry and liquid. But sort of
generic things like a bowl, even if you normally use the bowl
for liquids, you can use a bowl for solids as well. So
the מזרקות mizrakos that are used well, let's say let's say you
want to mix your עשרון Isaron of oil with your לוג Log
of שמן Shemen and you're going to mix it right into some
into this bowl that you normally use for catching the blood.
It doesn't sound too too appropriate but the question is does it
work? So he says these מזרקות, mizrakos, these large bowls that are
not measuring bowls, מקדשות את היבש. mekadeshos es hayavesh.
So even though they're normally used for for blood and for liquids,
if you can use them for dry things as well. שנאמר, Sheneemar,
the פסוק Pasuk says by the נשיאים, Nesiim, שניהם מלאים סלת בלולה
בשמן למנחה. Sheneihem meleim soles belula bashemen lemincha. The two of them,
and these were the מזרקות mizrakos because they were brand new you
mean. Yeah. Okay. Were filled with flour mixed with oil for a
מנחה. Mincha. So you see there that you can use them for
the dry. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to say that wasn't
really dry, that was mixed with oil. But before we get to
that question, what does this have to do with proving that a
that a לוג... Log... Liquid vessel rather than what does it do
with proving that a מנחה Mincha you can sanctify with the flour
alone? Here he's saying you can use a liquid vessel for
flour for dry products. Okay, but that doesn't prove that you can
sanctify dry by itself. I mean, the example he gives anyway is
flour mixed with the oil. So how do we know you can
sanctify the flour part of a מנחה Mincha by itself? So רש"י
Rashi has a very difficult read. תוספות Tosafot also struggles with explaining
what the proof is. In the end, תוספות Tosafot says well, maybe
here's the proof. Remember the whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara was
מדמינא מילתא למילתא. midamina milta l'milta. Can you learn one thing from
another even though they're not exactly applicable? So since שמואל Shmuel is
prepared to learn a הלכה Halacha from the נשיאים Nesi'im in the
מדבר, Midbar, which was obviously you know, you could have argued that
that was a special circumstance, that that was only at the time
of the מדבר, Midbar, and שמואל Shmuel is still ready to learn
a הלכה Halacha from there, so then obviously it would not be
such a jump to say that שמואל Shmuel would learn that since
you can bring a dry עשרון issaron by itself for a מנחת
חוטא, Minchat Chote, and that's sanctified, you can sanctify the flour by
itself even for a normal מנחה. Mincha. So it's not a very
satisfying point here. Okay, רש"י Rashi gives other answers; they're no more
satisfying.
A מנחת חוטא Minchat Chote doesn't need oil?
A
מנחת חוטא Minchat Chote is the one flour קרבן korban that does
not need oil. Okay, so that was the question: can we say
that since the כלי שרת klei sharet sanctify that flour by itself,
can they sanctify the flour of a מנחה Mincha by itself even
when it does need oil? Now again, there's no clear way to
see how you can get that out of שמואל's Shmuel statement. All
שמואל's Shmuel saying is that you can use a liquid vessel for
dry foods. So that's why רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot really have
a struggle inferring it from שמואל's Shmuel statement.
But when do you do a מנחת חוטא Minchat Chote instead of
a...?
Only for the cases mentioned at the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat
Vayikra, like somebody a does not have enough money for a more
expensive חטאת, Chatas, and b, it was a specific sin like entering
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash טמא, tamei, eating קרבנות korbanot טמא, tamei,
taking a... lying when it comes to a שבועה shvua about testifying
for עדות. eidus. סוטה Sotah is like... is in a similar category,
but it's not right. A סוטה Sotah would be the other case
where
it would be a מנחה mincha without oil. Okay, the מנחה mincha
that a סוטה Sotah brings. You had a question?
I had one on the name of the book. What is the...
oh, sorry. This is the Practical Dictionary by Frank. It's better than
Jastrow in two ways. Number one is it's got... it's got good
stuff in the back like ראשי תיבות Rashei Teivot and these charts,
although I should say that the huge $50 Steinsaltz introduction has charts.
And also it's like, you know, it does basically like the top
few thousand words. It doesn't have every single word. So it's a
quick reference but rather than having to, you know, go through a
million dictionary entries in Jastrow.
Wait, the עומר Omer does come with oil?
Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says... okay, so that was
the proof from שמואל, Shmuel, whatever the proof was. Now we're going
to focus on שמואל, Shmuel, who says that you can use these
liquid vessels if they're not measuring vessels for dry from this פסוק
pasuk about the נשיאים. Nesi'im. Now the question is the נשיאים Nesi'im
was mixed with oil. So אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar
lei Rav Acha miDifti l'Ravina, so he said to... רב אחא מדפתי
Rav Acha miDifti said to רבינא: Ravina: מנחה לחה היא, Mincha lacha
hi, a mincha, or you know, this mincha of that was brought
in the מדבר, Midbar, that was moist, it was mixed with oil.
אמר ליה לא נצרכא אלא ליבש שבה. Amar lei lo nitzrecha ela
l'yavesh shebah. No, this is for the dry part in it. So
what does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says well, presumably in any
מנחה mincha you don't mix it perfectly well, and there are clumps
of just, you know, flour without oil and it works to sanctify
even that, even though that this is primarily a liquid type of
a vessel. So that is an... again, not even very satisfying, another
not satisfying part of שמואל. Shmuel. Not only how is it an
evidence for what we were saying, but how does this prove that
a liquid vessel can sanctify dry? If you look at the parentheses,
again, fascinating, this is some gloss, but it gives a different explanation
than רש"י, Rashi, so let's read it. So what is the dry
part of a מנחה? mincha? דהיינו לבונה. dehainu levonah. Oh, the frankincense.
So you put לבונה levonah into this vessel, into this... so... and
it doesn't say it had לבונה? levonah? No, it does not. ואי
סלקא דעתך דסבר שמואל אין מנחה קדושה עד שיהיו כולן יבש כולן.
v'ee salka dachatach desavar Shmuel ein mincha k'dosha ad sheyihiyu kulan yavesh
kulan. And if שמואל Shmuel held that the מנחה mincha is not
holy until you know sanctified, this is also going back to the
basic proof that it works even for the
dry. עד שיהיו כולן יבש שבה היכי משכחת לה. ad sheyihiyu kulan
yavesh shebah heichi mashkachat lah. How does... how could שמואל Shmuel have
proven that this case by the נשיאים Nesi'im sanctified the dry?
והלא כולן לחין הן מהשמן. v'halo kulan lachin hen meihashemen. The לבונה
levonah would get moist because it would be on top of the
מנחה mincha which had oil. אלא שמע מינה קסבר שמואל היי בלא
היי. Ela shema mina kasavar Shmuel hai belo hai. So again, it's
not really... it's almost saying the... we'll use the problem of שמואל
Shmuel to answer both questions. We've got שמואל Shmuel who says look,
this thing that the נשיאים Nesi'im brought was dry and it was
being sanctified in a... it wasn't dry though. Well, that's the question.
But שמואל's Shmuel statement is it was dry and it was being
sanctified in a vessel that was used for liquid. So the גמרא's
Gemara question is it isn't dry. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is
ah, so obviously that's an obvious question, anybody can see it isn't
dry. What type of proof is שמואל... Shmuel... bringing? It must be
שמואל's Shmuel assuming that they not only brought the מנחה בלולה בשמן
Mincha belulah bashemen in it, but they even separately brought the לבונה
Levonah in it, which was totally dry. So from there you see
according to שמואל, Shmuel, you can say you can sanctify the independent
ingredient.
What do you mean? What do you mean? They first brought the
מנחה בלולה
בשמן,
Mincha
belulah bashemen,
they emptied it out, and then after, right.
And if you wouldn't have been assuming that, obviously this would have
been a silly proof. So and now that we see he must
be assuming that, we see he can sanctify the independent ingredients. But
of course, you know, it begs the question, what's the basis to
think that they were bringing independent לבונה? Levonah? So this is a
very difficult גמרא. Gemara. You don't understand שמואל's Shmuel basic statement, and
you don't understand how the גמרא Gemara is using it as proof
that you can sanctify the independent ingredients. So let's just finish this
up. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima, if you want you could say, מנחה
לגבי דם כיבש דמיא. Mincha legabei דם Dam ke’yavesh דם Damya. Okay,
that's more satisfying for שמואל's Shmuel original statement. That since this basic
מזרק Mizrak is used fundamentally for blood, and you're bringing it now
flour mixed with oil, although that is liquidy, it certainly would be
dry compared to blood, right? So if you had, so you have
דם Dam and you have this, you say this is a liquid
and this is fundamentally a non-liquid. So if something made for דם
Dam can use for a מנחה Mincha mixed with oil, you see
that when it's not a measuring vessel, you can use, you know,
liquid for dry, because it's still once it's not the measuring vessel,
it does not have to be distinct. Okay, that's a reasonable good
proof. Maybe it's not the exact same as totally dry, but it's
a reasonably good proof that even though something fundamentally for liquid, it
can sanctify dry.
Would you use the same scaling for מנחה Mincha and an animal?
That's what שמואל Shmuel is saying.
For דם Dam and for a מנחה, Mincha, that's what שמואל's Shmuel
saying. Michael's offended by the aesthetics or the cleanliness of it, but
maybe you clean it out. And שמואל Shmuel is saying it would
work to sanctify. That's, that's שמואל's Shmuel statement. Now again, the evidence
isn't great, but at least now it's better than it was. What
relevance that has to sanctifying the independent ingredients is extremely unclear.
But someone's eating this at any time?
No, that's not true. The מנחה Mincha would be eaten. Who eats
it? The כהנים. Kohanim. Yeah. But again, I mean, you would be
offended if you cleaned it out really well. It was all dry,
it was all, it was, it wasn't absorbed, it was like silver,
it was, it was דם, Dam, it wasn't heated, it was cold.
You would refuse to use that after something had been used for
דם? Dam?
No, I would be fine with it. I just say, you know,
the whole idea of water at the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash doesn't
seem like it was in abundance.
That's a good point, too. Okay, so let's keep on going.
It's hard to actually operate on a large...
right,
got it.
No, my point was that this whole thing was new anyway. So
doesn't it prove that once you've used it for דם, Dam, you
can go ahead and use it for...
right, right, exactly. Okay, so let's just review what we said. There's
a debate whether the כלי שרת Klei shares operate on independent ingredients.
We know they can work on those ingredients by themselves when they
are the whole קרבן Korban that's being brought. Can they work on
independent ingredients? That is the debate of רב Rav and רבי חנינא.
Rebbi Chanina. We tried to prove it from a statement about שמואל,
Shmuel, which was very unclear how we're proving it, but at the
end of the day, anyway, שמואל Shmuel did make a statement that
although you can't use measuring vessels for dry for liquid and liquid
for dry, you can use generic liquid vessels that are made for
דם, Dam, you can use them even for things like a מנחה.
Mincha. Let's go on. So now the גמרא Gemara says: גופא. Gufa.
Let's look at a statement we quoted earlier, yesterday. אמר רבי אלעזר:
Amar Reb Elazar: מנחה שקמצה בהיכל כשירה. Mincha shekamtza baheichal kesheira. If
you do the קמיצה Kemitza of a מנחה Mincha in the היכל,
Heichal, in the very, you know, place, the היכל Heichal where the
שלחן Shulchan is, that would be
kosher. So we'll see what I might have thought. שכן מצינו בסידור
בזיכין, Sheken matzinu besidur bazichin, that's what you find by the לחם
הפנים, Lechem hapanim, which is a type of a מנחה, Mincha, and
you remove the part that's going to be offered off, the little
spoons of incense, in the היכל. Heichal. So
מתיב רבי ירמיה: Masiv Reb Yirmiah: So רבי ירמיה Reb Yirmiah asked:
וקמץ משם ממקום שרגלי הזר עומדות, Vekamatz misham mimakom sheraglei hazar omdos,
that you shall take the קמיצה Kemitza from there, where the non-כהן
Kohen is standing. What's the question?
That is בתחילה, Bit’chila, he’s in the same place.
One minute, one minute, but maybe it's not. Okay, one minute. So
that's telling you that presumably you don't have to be to the
north of the מזבח, Mizbeach, let's say that's what it says. Wherever
a זר Zar can stand, you can take it. But he’s going
to learn it, not only is it allowing you to take it
from anywhere a זר Zar can stand, maybe it has to be
where the non-כהן Kohen was standing. The non-כהן Kohen brings his מנחה,
Mincha, the כהן Kohen takes it, and a non-כהן Kohen is not
allowed to be standing in the היכל. Heichal.
So the only way it worked for לחם הפנים Lechem hapanim is
because that's where it has to be?
Yeah, and you don't have that פסוק, Pasuk, and you don't have
this non-כהן Kohen bringing it. All right, and then it quotes the
end of this ברייתא: Braisa: בן בתירה אומר: Ben Beseira omer: מניין
שאם קמץ בשמאל שיחזיר ויקמוץ בימין? Minayin she’im kamatz bismol sheyachzir veyikmotz
biyamin? Going back to our משנה. Mishna. How do you know if
you took it in the left, you can go back and put
it back and take it with
the right? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: וקמץ משם, Vekamatz misham, take from
there, the קמיצה, Kemitza, take a handbreadth. ממקום שקמץ כבר, Mimakom shekamatz
kvar, you can take the handbreadth from the same place you took
it before. If you made a mistake, put it back and start
again. Anyway, we have the first part of this ברייתא Braisa that
says the non-כהן Kohen has to bring it and stand there. You
can't do that in the היכל. Heichal. So the גמרא Gemara says:
איכא דאמרי, Ika de’amri, some say, הוא מתיב לה והוא מפרק לה.
Hu masiv lah vehu mifarek lah. He asked the question and then
he gave the answer to the question. איכא דאמרי, Ika de’amri, and
some say no, the answer was given by somebody else. אמר ליה...
Amar lei... Rabbi Yaakov to Rabbi Yirmiya bar Tachlifa. So Rabbi Yaakov
said to Rabbi Yirmiya bar Tachlifa, אסבירה לך, Asbira lach, let me
explain it to you. לא נצרכה אלא להכשיר את כל העזרה כולה.
Lo nitzrecha ela l'hachshir es kol ha'azarah kulo. When it says the
Kohen takes it from where the Zar stands, it doesn't mean that
it has to be where the Zar is, the non-Kohen is allowed
to stand, it must be there to exclude the היכל. Heichal. It
means it may be there. It could be anywhere in the עזרה.
Azara. What would I have thought? Why would I have thought it
could not be anywhere in the עזרה? Azara? שלא תאמר, Shelo tomar,
you should not say, הואיל ועולה קדשי קדשים ומנחה קדשי קדשים, Ho'il
v'olah kodshei kodashim u'mincha kodshei kodashim, since both an עולה Olah and
a מנחה Mincha are קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim and again the basic
definition of קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim is once they go into the
מקדש Mikdash they don't leave. So they're both, the עולה Olah is
totally burnt and the מנחה Mincha is totally, the remnant is eaten.
So I would have said, מה עולה טעונה צפון אף מנחה
טעונה צפון? Mah olah te'unah tzafon af mincha te'unah tzafon? An עולה
Olah needs the north, right? The characteristic of all קדשי קדשים Kodshei
Kodashim is they need to be the north of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach.
Maybe the מנחה Mincha does. So therefore it says where the זר
Zar stands. No, it can be anywhere in the עזרה. Azara. So
again the question is if it says the זר Zar stands, shouldn't
that exclude the היכל Heichal where a non-כהן Kohen is not allowed?
And we're saying, no, no, that's not coming to limit, that's coming
to include, and it's including that it doesn't have to be to
the north. Don't think it's קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim it has to
be to the north, it can be anywhere. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, I never would have thought the north. Why?
Because I would have said מה עולה שכן כליל, Mah olah shekein
kalil, you can't learn from an עולה Olah to a מנחה. Mincha.
An עולה Olah is fully burnt, it's more strict. Okay, learn from
a חטאת. Chatas. מחטאת, Meichatas, so learn from a חטאת. Chatas. No,
מה חטאת שכן מכפרת, Mah chatas shekein mechaperes, that has the power
to atone, which is not true about
a
מנחה. Mincha. או חייבי כריתות, O chayavei krisos, על מאשם, al me'asham,
learn from an אשם. Asham. מה אשם שכן מיני דמים. Mah asham
shekein minei damim. At least an אשם Asham even when it's not
coming to atone is at least blood. And this is interesting because
it goes to the question of hierarchy, and the גמרא Gemara is
going to say you can't learn from the animal sacrifices which are
in the north because they're all animals and you can't apply it
to a מנחה. Mincha. Now, does it just mean they're a distinct
category because they're animals, or does it mean, right, they're weightier because
they're animals? Usually, the גמרא Gemara is not just looking for a
point of distinction, usually, in this type of a framing, it's saying
that it's weightier. But it's not clear. Maybe it's saying that that
makes it enough of a different category that you cannot apply it.
I would still say my question from the very beginning, עולה למנחה,
חטאת למנחה. Olah l'mincha, chatas l'mincha. I understand.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara uses that פסוק Pasuk when it wants. I
know. Okay, so שכן מכולהו נמי, Shekein mikulhu nami,
you can't ask from any of the animal
sacrifices, שכן מיני דמים, shekein minei damim, they all have blood and
therefore what you require by them you do not necessarily require by
a מנחה. Mincha. I could have said that from the beginning. I
know. אלא איצטריך, Ela itztarich, סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, you're
right. I wouldn't have thought it had to be the north. I
would have known don't apply animal criteria to מנחה, Mincha, but I
still would have thought it couldn't have been the whole עזרה. Azara.
Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought הואיל
וכתיב והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה אל המזבח, Ho'il u'chsiv v'hikrivah el hakohen
v'higishah el hamizbe'ach, that the owner brings it to the כהן Kohen
and the כהן Kohen touches it to the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. And then
it says וקמץ משם, V'kamatz misham, he takes the קמיצה. kmitza. So
where does he touch it to the מזבח? Mizbe'ach? So he says
הגשה בקרן דרומית מערבית. Hagashah b'keren dromis ma'aravis. We learn from elsewhere
that you touch it at the southwest corner. Why? Because it's פני
המזבח, pnei hamizbe'ach, the face, because the כבש ramp is on the
south. Here, here's my כבש. ramp. The כבש ramp is on the
south, so that is the face, so the face is the south.
And it says פתח אהל מועד pesach ohel moed facing the אהל
מועד, Ohel Moed, which is over there in the west, so it's
the southwest corner. Okay, so he touches it on the southwest corner
and then he takes the קמיצה. kmitza. So I would have thought
מה הגשה בקרן דרומית מערבית, mah hagashah b'keren dromis ma'aravis,
the same way he touches it on the southwest corner, אף קמיצה
נמי בקרן דרומית מערבית, af kmitza nami b'keren dromis ma'aravis,
therefore he must take the קמיצה kmitza from there because then it
actually, that would be a good read of the פסוק, Pasuk, וקמץ
משם, v'kamatz misham,
from there where he just was after having touched it to the
מזבח. Mizbe'ach. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. So therefore it says,
no, wherever the זר Zar can stand. So again the point is
on the one hand we say you can take it in the
היכל Heichal because that's where you do the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim.
Ah, the פסוק Pasuk says where a זר Zar can stand and
a זר Zar can't stand in the היכל. Heichal. And the answer
is a זר Zar can stand is not saying a זר Zar
must be able to stand there. It says even where a זר
Zar can stand and you're allowed to do the קמיצה kmitza anywhere
in the עזרה. Azara. Okay, גופא. Gufa. Now we're going back to
all these earlier statements. So we talked about a מנחה Mincha in
the עזרה, Azara, now we're going to talk about, I mean in
the היכל, Heichal, now we're going to talk about שלמים Shlamim in
the היכל. Heichal. אמר רבי יוחנן שלמים ששחטן בהיכל כשרים, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Shlamim sheshachatan b'Heichal kshairim, שנאמר ושחטו פתח אהל מועד, shene'emar v'shachato
pesach ohel moed, you shall slaughter, if you slaughter a שלמים Shlamim
in the היכל Heichal it's kosher because it says slaughter it by
the opening of the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So it's in reference
to the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. ולא יהיה טפל חמור מן העיקר,
V'lo yehei tafel chamur min ha'ikar, and what is sort of derivative
should not be more strict than the fundamental. Since it's about relating
to the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, if you're in the אהל מועד...
Ohel Moed... in the היכל, Heichal, נאָך בעסער, noch besser, it's even
better. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you
on this, רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר, Rebi Yehuda ben Beseira Omer,
מניין שהמקיף עבודת כוכבים את העזרה כשהכהנים נכנסים להיכל ואוכלים בקדשי קדשים
ובשירי מנחות? minayin shehamakif avodas kochavim es ha'azarah keshehakohanim nichnasim laheichal ve'ochlim
bekodshei kodashim uvishiyarei menachos?
How do I know? It's like just a very, you know, gripping
image. I know, yes, you know, sometimes certain סוגיות sugyos are repeated.
Okay, how do you know if non-Jews are surrounding, are have attacking,
right, they've broken into the מקדש, Mikdash, and they're in the עזרה,
Azarah, and so what are the כהנים Kohanim going to do? They're
going to run into the, you know, into the היכל, Heichal, which
had doors, and it was, you know, had walls, so that was
the only place they could go, and there what did they have?
With them they have their קרבנות. korbanos. So they want to know,
are they allowed to eat their קרבנות korbanos there? Which is not
a trivial question. If you're being besieged by the non-Jews, you want
to be eating. So anyway, so it says how do you know
that they're allowed to eat their קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim in the
היכל Heichal and the remnant of the מנחות? menachos? תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, the verse teaches, top of ט עמוד א, tes amud aleph,
בקדש הקדשים תאכלנו. bekodesh hakodashim tochelenu.
You shall eat it in the Holy of Holies. Now in the
context of that verse, it was referring to the עזרה, Azarah, but
we are using that verse out of context to say the Holy
of Holies, which is basically the היכל, Heichal, not, well not literally
the Holy of Holies, but at least the היכל. Heichal. So the
גמרא Gemara says, why do you need a פסוק? pasuk? So I'm
not debating the דין, din, but why do you need a פסוק?
pasuk? והלמה לי קרא, vahalamah li kra,
why do I need a פסוק? pasuk? לימא, leima, why didn't you
say the same קל וחומר kal vachomer logic you said before? Since
normally we're told בחצר אהל מועד יאכלוה, bechatzer ohel moed yocheluha, which
is by the way that פסוק pasuk of בקדש הקדשים, bekodesh hakodashim,
בקדש הקדשים תאכלנו בחצר אהל מועד יאכלוה. bekodesh hakodashim tochelenu bechatzer ohel
moed yocheluha. So since it already says you eat קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim in the courtyard of the אהל מועד, ohel moed, so it's
referenced to the אהל מועד, ohel moed, so certainly you should be
able to eat it in the אהל מועד ohel moed itself. So
why don't we make the same קל וחומר, kal vachomer, who needs
a פסוק? pasuk? We've already seen that then, yes,
this is like פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Why?
Well
that would be true anyway, that would be true anyway, the פיקוח
נפש. pikuach nefesh. So I was just describing the scenario like that
to make it a little bit more come alive. I know.
It's implied that way.
Yeah, let's say the question is that they had with them other
stuff to eat as well, and it wasn't פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
Is there any problem with them eating this? Like, you know, let's
frame it this way, they had other food, but if they don't
eat this food it'll become נותר. nosar. Are they allowed to eat
this so it doesn't become נותר? nosar? But I know, then it's
sort of like you have to have this picture like they're being
attacked by the non-Jews and you know, they're besieged and the only
thing they're worried about here is the נותר. nosar. But they were
very, they were very פרום frum the כהנים, Kohanim, they're worried about
it, yes.
And I'd say the גמרא Gemara could have found better נותר.
nosar. Yes I know, but it's more interesting in saying that they
can eat it in the היכל Heichal than... the real question is
why did it bother giving that as the extreme example, you know?
But because as we'll see in a minute, that even though they're
allowed to eat it in the היכל, Heichal, it's not appropriate. Okay,
yeah Rachel, you wanted to ask something?
I'm just confused, the part you take קמיצה kemitza from, is that
the part you're not going to eat or the part you're...
the part your קמיצה kemitza is burnt and the rest you eat.
So when you say you can do קמיצה kemitza or שלמים shlamim
in the היכל, Heichal, you're not eating them in the היכל, Heichal,
you're basically... you're basically either slaughtering it in the היכל, Heichal, taking
the קמיצה, kemitza, but here's the first time we mentioned eating in
the היכל, Heichal, and that's the point the גמרא Gemara is going
to emphasize, that eating is less obvious than the other things. Okay,
so which is why they probably gave the example of having no
options, because you should not be eating in the היכל. Heichal. So
let's see the גמרא's Gemara answer. Let me just read the answer.
Okay. So the גמרא's Gemara question is why not use a קל
וחומר? kal vachomer? Why did you need a פסוק pasuk to tell
me you can eat it in the היכל? Heichal? Use the same
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So the גמרא Gemara says עבודה, avodah, when
it comes to doing an actual part of the ritual of the
קרבנות, korbanos, דאדם עובד במקום רבו אמרינן, de'adam oved bemakom rabbo amrinan,
we say that you could do service to your master like in
the presence of your master, in the place. You could be in
his bedroom and you know setting his bed and attending to him
or whatever. So you could be doing service to God in the
היכל. Heichal. That we say שלא יהא טפל חמור מן העיקר. shelo
yehei tafel chamur min ha'ikar. If you serve him outside of the
chamber, you serve him in the chamber as well. אכילה, achilah, but
eating, שאין אדם אוכל במקום רבו, she'ein adam ochel bemakom rabbo,
normally we say a person should not be eating in the place
of his master. So therefore you would not have said just because
you can eat in the courtyard you can eat in the היכל.
Heichal. So טעמא דכתב קרא, taama dechasav kra, it's because the verse
says it. הלא כתב קרא, halo chasav kra, if the verse had
not written it, לא יהא טפל חמור מן העיקר לא אמרינן. lo
yehei tafel chamur min ha'ikar lo amrinan. We would not say that
inside is better than outside. Eating is less dignified and appropriate, and
the interesting thing to note here is we always say that the
eating of the כהנים Kohanim is part of the עבודה. avodah. כהנים
אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים. Kohanim ochlim uv'alim miskaprin. And then when the כהנים
Kohanim eat, the owners are atoned. The eating of the כהנים Kohanim
is like the eating of the מזבח, Mizbeiach, but nevertheless there is
something less, you know, dignified about eating, something that more at the
same time, you know, a) it's messy, b) you're also satisfying your
appetite even though it is an עבודה, avodah, that is not as
appropriate במקום רבו. bemakom rabbo. So you don't make that. קל וחומר
kal v'chomer and it's also why they gave the scenario presumably of
having no choice, of being surrounded, because as opposed to the other
things where it's okay, you can do it in the היכל, Heichal,
this is something which has to be which is only if there's
absolutely no other choice. You had a question, Michael?
No, I was gonna say, I mean if you say that קל
וחומר kal v'chomer then you'd say even eat in the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim because if you can eat in the חטאת Chatat then
you'd certainly eat in the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Maybe that's why
you have a...
קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim we know is limited in terms of who
has access at what time. Since at least the היכל Heichal כהנים
Kohanim have the right to have access, the only question is do
they have right to do the עבודה. avoda. Okay.
But the פסוק pasuk doesn't even say you can't.
What? The פסוק pasuk doesn't say you can eat it.
Well it says קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim תאכלו, tochlu, תאכלנו.
tochlenu. בקדש הקדשים. Bakodesh HaKodashim.
So the rest of
the פסוק pasuk talks about...
I know, so that's that's a דרשה drasha of חז"ל Chazal that
קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim taken a little out of context of the
פסוק pasuk means even in the היכל. Heichal. Okay. So now we
have determined that what can be done in the היכל, Heichal, the
קמיצה, kmitza, the שחיטה, shchita, and when necessary even the אכילה achila
based on a פסוק. pasuk. Okay. Now it's more. Now we are
going to get back to the מנחה mincha discussion and where the
כלי שרת klei shares and how the כלי שרת klei shares operate.
So let's take a look. איתמר, itmar,
בללה balala חוץ לחומת עזרה. chutz l'chomat azara. You mixed it outside
of the עזרה. Azara. Now this is everybody...
I mean this is if you did it, right?
If. You mixed it. Okay now everybody was asking from the beginning
how did this whole process take place? Let's take a stop and
say what do we already know? We know that we had discussed
before whether you need a... where... we
had discussed before whether the כלי שרת kli shares has to be
held by the כהן Kohen or not. At most we said it
had to be held by the כהן Kohen when you do the
קמיצה kmitza but not at the earlier stage. But we implicitly said
that you were using a כלי שרת. kli shares. So when you
take the flour and the oil from your home, right, and the
גמרא Gemara even used the phrase מביא מתוך ביתו meivi mitoch beiso
when it was talking about like you know you mess something up
and you have to מביא מתוך ביתו, meivi mitoch beiso, you put
it in a כלי שרת kli shares and you do the mixing.
So what we all and what... that's number one, that the mixing
and the creating of the מנחה mincha is in a כלי שרת.
kli shares. One second. The other thing we know though is that
you don't need a כהן Kohen at that stage because it says
מקמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה, mikmitza v'eilach mitzvas kehuna, that the כהן Kohen
only starts from doing the קמיצה. kmitza. So here you are, maybe
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash lends you the כלי שרת, kli shares,
you're mixing it, I mean maybe they used כהנים Kohanim to do
it anyway but על פי דין, al pi din, you're mixing it
in the כלי שרת. klei shares.
So we don't know where.
That's the exact question we're about to ask. And then the כהן
Kohen takes it. And now the question is so you need to
use a כלי שרת kli shares but does it have to be
done in the המקדש Mikdash or not? You had a question.
Was just wondering about is there a... I mean we covered this...
is there a minimum or or a specific amount that you're supposed
to bring?
Yeah of flour? Yeah that's what we've been talking, איסרון isaron is
the minimum. And the... there cannot be a מנחה mincha less than
an איסרון isaron of flour and that an איסרון isaron we said
was about and a לוג log of שמן. shemen.
So איסרון isaron is exactly what it
is...
you could bring more for a מנחת נדבה, minchas nidava, yeah. But
for מנחת נסכים minchas n'sachim or something there it is very fixed
amounts based on the
animal.
No but also when I bring my עולה olah or I bring
a שלמים shlamim there's a specific מנחה mincha that goes with it.
A מנחת נסכים minchas n'sachim that goes with it.
What about all the מנחות minchos in ויקרא?
Vayikra? All the מנחות minchos in ויקרא Vayikra which are all מנחת
נדבה, minchas nidava,
there I can bring more. But they have to be like... we'll
see about we'll see about how the gradations work. Okay.
People who raise their hands get preference. Yeah. What?
No, you don't, you bring the flour, you bring the oil, you
mix it in a כלי שרת kli shares and now we're going
to talk about where that mixing took place. Yes, Raso.
Is the כהן Kohen allowed to make a meal out of somebody's
מנחה mincha and somebody's...
Sure. Yeah.
Yes. Mixed together?
Yeah. Yeah. Okay yes.
So my question is, is there no... was there no quality control?
In other words, how... it's supposed to bring סולת, soles, like I
bring it from my house. How do they know?
Maybe they checked it before they gave you the כלי שרת kli
shares to use, I don't know. It's a good question. I don't
know. It's a good question, but maybe they did, especially if you
needed the כלי שרת kli shares maybe they did. Yeah because you're
right they checked קורבנות korbanos for מום. mum. Right, exactly.
So you put oil in the flour and this this makes bread?
This... well, it makes an oil and flour mixture.
There's water too. What? Water too. Raw cookie dough.
I know, so we're going to see there are different types of
מנחות. minchos. Some are just oil and flour, some are oil and
flour baked and so on.
Bread on
the table?
I know, so we're going to see.
There's different... what? What? Okay good. Alright, so let's take a look.
Alright, so now we know where it's what it's done in is
a כלי שרת kli shares and it's done by the owner and
now the question is where is it done? So let's take a
look.
איתמר, itmar, בללה balala חוץ לחומת עזרה. chutz l'chomat azara. You did
it outside of the wall of the המקדש. Mikdash. That would be
even in the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, again עזרה Azara means the
עזרת ישראל. Ezras Yisrael. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar פסולה, psula,
it's invalid.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר amar כשרה, ksheira, it's kosher. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish אמר amar כשרה ksheira דכתיב d'chsiv ויצוק... vayitzok... ויצק עליה
שמן ונתן עליה לבונה, v'yatzak aleha shemen v'natan aleha levona, pour oil
then put the לבונה levona on it, והדר, v'hadar, and then והביאה
אל בני אהרן הכהנים, v'hevi'a el bnei Aharon hakohanim, you brought it
to the sons of Aaron the priests, וקמץ, v'kamatz, and then the
כהן kohen takes the קמיצה. kmitza. So until the קמיצה kmitza you're
doing it. מקמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה. mikmitza v'eilach mitzat kehuna. From קמיצה
kmitza onwards is when the כהנים kohanim get involved. לימד על יציקה
ובלילה שכשירה בזר. limad al yitzika u'vlila shekshara b'zar. So therefore the
יציקה, yitzika, the pouring of the oil in, and the בלילה, blila,
the mixing of the oil, can be done by a non-כהן. kohen.
ומדכהונה לא בעיא פנים נמי לא בעיא. u'midekehuna lo ba'ya pnim nami
lo ba'ya. And since you don't need a כהן, kohen, פנים נמי
לא בעיא, pnim nami lo ba'ya, you also don't need the מקדש.
Mikdash. This is something that you can do in your own home.
ורבי יוחנן אמר פסולה, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar psula, it's invalid. כיון דעשייתה
בכלי keivan d'asiyata b'kli or בכלי b'keli הוא, hu, since you do
it in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, so it requires it to
be sanctified in the process. נהי דכהונה לא בעיא פנים מיהא בעיא.
nehi dekehuna lo ba'ya pnim miha ba'ya. It does not need a
כהן, kohen, but it needs to be done in the מקדש. Mikdash.
This is a process of sanctifying it. Now it's again interesting to
think about the animal analog, because by animals I sanctify it with
my words. הרי זו עולה. harei zu ola. Here I sanctify it,
part of what a מנחה mincha requires, I can say by the
flour, you know, זו, zu, this is קדוש kadosh for a מנחה.
mincha. But part of the sanctity requires even before you do the
קמיצה, kmitza, it to be elevated by a כלי. kli. So it
requires something that you don't have by a קרבן. korban. So maybe
the fact that it needs a כלי שרת kli sharet also requires
the environment of the מקדש, Mikdash, because it requires the whole sort
of special, you know, מקדש Mikdash apparatus to raise its sanctity the
same way it does by כלי שרת. klei sharet. One second. So
the only debate here is whether it is required as a biological
extension of the כלי שרת. kli sharet. There is a long תוספות
Tosafot that has another problem. He says, I don't get it. If
you're using a כלי שרת kli sharet according to ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish outside of the מקדש, Mikdash, and now you've sanctified it, and
now what the כלי שרת kli sharet adds is called קדושת הגוף.
kdushat haguf. It's not only sanctified because I've designated it, it's intrinsically
sanctified, which means that it can become פסול pasul now and cannot
be redeemed. If it becomes פסול pasul I can't redeem it. It's
not just like I sanctified my car. It has intrinsic קדושה. kdusha.
So he says, well one of the things you can't do with
something that has קדושת הגוף kdushat haguf is take it out of
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. That was my question.
Thank you.
So I knew it was going to be your question. So I'm
sorry.
Well I was guessing. So the תוספות, Tosafot, it's very nice that
you can say in terms of process it doesn't require מקדש, Mikdash,
but once it's קדוש, kadosh, how can it be out of the
בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? So תוספות Tosafot says, we see from this
גמרא Gemara that even once you know it sort of like okay
we see otherwise, we see that even once a מנחה mincha becomes
קדוש kadosh in the כלי, kli, it's not פסול ביוצא, pasul b'yotze,
because that's never even raised. Even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't raise
it, meaning it becomes invalid when it goes out of the מקדש.
Mikdash. Even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan does not raise that as why
he wants it in the מקדש. Mikdash.
Maybe it's a process of leaving the מקדש.
Mikdash. Maybe it's a process of leaving the מקדש, Mikdash, that's an
interesting thought, or maybe I think תוספות Tosafot does not phrase it
that way. תוספות Tosafot says the קדושה kdusha of the מנחה mincha
is such, and this would be the logic, it's sort of like
maybe you know self... it's maybe like circular. If you say you
don't introduce the כהן kohen until a later stage, and it's something
for the owners to do, then maybe the תורה Torah is also
telling you it's something for the owners to do in their home.
And therefore the תורה Torah is explicitly making it an exception and
saying even when it becomes sanctified, being out of the מקדש Mikdash
is not yet a problem until you engage the כהנים kohanim and
do the קמיצה. kmitza.
Maybe you could put it in, maybe it has status of from
outside to in, but not in to out.
That's sort of what James was saying. But again think about the
analog of שחיטה. shchita. שחיטה shchita can be done by a non-כהן,
kohen, but you have to do the שחיטה shchita in the מקדש.
Mikdash. But again שחיטה shchita is the עבודה. avoda. קמיצה kmitza is
also the עבודה. avoda. קמיצה kmitza does have to be done inside.
So here you have something that is a process of כלי שרת,
klei sharet, of sanctifying it and קדושת הגוף, kdushat haguf, but maybe
it's a process that because it's for the owners to do, we're
not, you know, it's excluded from the problem of being outside the
מקדש. Mikdash. And neither רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish raise that issue. Yeah.
That makes sense because the animal is already an animal and you
can take the animal outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. You have
to actually create the
מנחה mincha there out
in order to say this is the thing that I will bring
as a קרבן. korban. So the human being creates something that has
already been created and sanctified.
No, you can do the whole thing in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash if you want to.
No, but what she's saying is even the animal works without the
כלי שרת kli sharet is because the animal is already in its
full state. This is something that is manufactured. Since it's manufactured, then
you know to be designated and identified it sort of needs the
sanctity of the כלי.
kli. One second. Actually I misunderstood something. Right. Right. Right. Wait,
I want to make sure I understood. So according to both ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, then you need to
use, you have to have done all this in a כלי שרת?
kli sharet? Or not? Yes. Right. So basically what you're doing is
according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, you go, you go to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, take a כלי שרת, kli sharet, you borrow
it, you go, you're going home and then you're mixing it all.
Right. Or maybe you're just doing it in the עזרת נשים. ezrat
nashim. They'll say to you, you know, like when you go to
the post office, they say fill out this form, go over there,
fill it out, when you're done, come back. So you go there,
take this כלי שרת, kli sharet, go over there in the עזרת
נשים. ezrat nashim. Wait, are you making an analogy? Making an analogy.
It's a good analogy.
Make your מנחה, mincha, when you're done, come back.
Wait, would they actually let, what?
Would the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
actually let, lend כלי שרת klei sharet to people to go home?
But that's what I'm saying, maybe it's not go home. Maybe it's
like go over to that counter, go over into the עזרת נשים,
ezrat nashim, get out of the way, make your כלי שרת. kli
sharet.
Wait, it's like the case of מביא מתוך ביתו, mevi mitoch beito,
which to me, you know,
well that was maybe being מביא mevi the ingredients מתוך ביתו. mitoch
beito. I mean, you know, I think your question is good. I
don't know if they lent out the כלי שרת klei sharet to
take it home, but they might have lent it out to take
it into the עזרת נשים. ezrat nashim. Right. Alright, so let's take
a look.
כלי שרת klei sharet means it's sanctified vessels? Yeah, yeah. Not just
any pottery?
No, that's the whole point of being a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
Okay. You can't have it out of pottery anyway. Okay, so let's
take a look. It seems like רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Okay.
So, okay. Ta-da-da. Where are we?
So
חומת העזרה. chomat ha'azarah.
We don't mean like, the עזרה azarah is עזרת ישראל. ezrat Yisrael.
It is not the חומת המקדש. chomat haMikdash. Correct. Okay. Okay, so
דהא רבי יוחנן
אמר, de'ha Rebbi Yochanan amar, and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says פסולה.
psulah. I think I read this. כיון דעשייתה בכלי היא, keivan de'asiyata
bikli hee, since you make it in the כלי, kli, נהי דכהונה
לא בעיא, nehee de'kehunah lo ba'aya, you don't need a כהן, kohen,
but פנים מיהא בעיא, panim miha ba'aya, you need the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, tanya kavatei de'Rebbi Yochanan, we learn
like רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. בללה זר כשרה, balalah zar kisherah, if
a non-כהן kohen mixes it, it's כשר. kasher. חוץ לחומת העזרה פסולה,
chutz lechomat ha'azarah psulah, but if it's done outside the walls of
the עזרה, azarah, it is invalid. So there you go, we learn
like רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. You liked ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because
it was a more interesting position. Okay. איתמר, itmar, now we're going
to have another debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. מנחה שחסרה קודם קמיצה. mincha shechasrah kodem kmitzah. So we
had discussed this before by the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, if the
מנחה, mincha, a piece of it was lacking before the קמיצה, kmitzah,
can you refill it from your own ingredients? רבי יוחנן אמר יביא
מתוך ביתו וימלאנה, Rebbi Yochanan amar yavi mitoch beito veyimla'enah, bring ingredients
from your house and fill it up. ריש לקיש אמר לא יביא
מתוך ביתו וימלאנה, Reish Lakish amar lo yavi mitoch beito veyimla'enah, you
cannot bring ingredients from your house and fill it up, it is
already invalid, throw it out, start again. רבי יוחנן אמר מביא מתוך
ביתו וימלאנה, Rebbi Yochanan amar mevi mitoch beito veyimla'enah, bring from your
house and fill it up.
I know. קמיצה קבעה. kmitzah kav’ah. Only when you do the קמיצה
kmitzah is it designated like this now defines it fully as a
מנחה. mincha. And therefore, prior to that, if a little was lacking,
you can re-add more and re-make it a מנחה. mincha. Only the
קמיצה kmitzah defines, you know, the exact identity of the object. Now
as Michael says, it's a little opposite of what we said before,
because, you know, you would think that if until the קמיצה kmitzah
it's not yet fully designated, he might be more liberal about letting
you do it outside, mixing it and then bringing it in, because
the קמיצה kmitzah is what really like fully designates it. So I
think that's a very good point. Yes, it's not, you know, logically
you would have expected those to go together and they do not.
But he is now saying not that the קמיצה kmitzah fully sanctifies
it, but it's קבעה, kav'ah, like defines that these are the exact
parameters of it and you cannot add any more. Before קמיצה kmitzah
you can add if if some fell away. And רבי יוחנן, Rebbi
Yochanan, so what? קמיצה קבעה. kmitzah kav’ah. ריש לקיש אמר לא יביא
מתוך ביתו וימלאנה, Reish Lakish amar lo yavi mitoch beito veyimla'enah, you
cannot fill it back from your house, קדושת כלי קבעה, kedushat kli
kav'ah, the sanctity of the כלי kli designates it. So even though
he said that sanctity works outside the מקדש, Mikdash, but he still
says it still sanctifies it. And once that is sanctified as the
מנחה, mincha, then nothing else can be this מנחה. mincha. And if
some got lacking, you cannot add more.
Doesn't matter, each מנחה mincha is separate. Okay. איתיביה רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש, eiteivei Rebbi Yochanan le'Reish Lakish, so רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
asked ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, חסר הלוג, chasar halog, we talk about
the לוג log שמן shemen of the מצורע, metzora, that if some
of it spilled before you got around to doing the עבודה avodah
with the מצורע, metzora, אם עד שלא יצק, im ad shelo yatzak,
if you have yet to pour into the כהן's kohen hand, right?
The תורה Torah says the כהן kohen pours from the לוג log
onto his hand and puts on the right ear and thumb and
the toe of the מצורע. metzora. So this ברייתא braita teaches if
some of it spilled before you poured, so then ימלאנו, yimla'enu, fill
it back up. And that's exactly analogous to some of the מנחה
mincha was lacking before the קמיצה kmitzah was taken. So גמרא Gemara
says תיובתא. tiyuvta. Okay, that is an absolute question on ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan batting a thousand here.
Yeah, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is doing very, very well.
Doesn't he usually say, I mean between רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, the הלכה? halacha? We rule
like רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan in general anyways, but if there's evidence
otherwise we would rule like to the opposite, like ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish we would rule like it. איתמר, itmar, now we have another
debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, or
רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, so let's take a look. You see they
really learned, they really got into מנחות. Menachot. I mean I'm serious,
like if you remember when we did זבחים, Zevachim, we did not
see רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that frequently.
So it's like interesting to see which, you know, אמוראים Amoraim dominate
more in which מסכתות. masechtot. So anyway,
שיריים... shirayim...
Yes, but the comment you just made that some אמוראים Amoraim dominate
more?
Yeah, that's really interesting.
Because that speaks with some people not liking it.
Yeah, or not finding it as interesting or... well, I don't know
it's about קרבנות. korbanos. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish are very dominant in מנחות Menachos and not so dominant in
זבחים. Zevachim. So it might just be intellectual interest. You know, I
really don't know how to... you know, but it is interesting. There's
definitely a different distribution of אמוראים Amoraim in each מסכתא. masechta.
What do you make of it?
Ah, you know, different people had different areas of interest. Specialists. Yeah.
Okay. So, I'll say just a
brief parenthetical comment. So about a hundred and fifty years ago, we
don't have a ירושלמי Yerushalmi on קדשים. Kodshim. Although the רמב"ם Rambam
in פירוש המשניות Peirush HaMishnayos says it exists. We've never had anybody
quote it in any manuscript of it. About a hundred and sixty
years ago somebody discovered a ירושלמי Yerushalmi on קדשים Kodshim and came
out with it and wrote a whole commentary on it and showed
how the commentary explained a lot of difficult רמב"םs, Rambams, because it's
consistent because רמב"ם Rambam claims we had it. Anyway, a lot of
people believed it. The משנה ברורה, Mishna Berurah, the חפץ חיים Chafetz
Chaim thought it was genuine, he quotes it in the משנה ברורה.
Mishna Berurah. But a lot of people were extremely skeptical and it
was not too long afterwards it was proven to be a fraud.
It's one of, yes, it's one of the greatest forgeries of Jewish
books.
This guy made it up?
Yeah, he totally made it up. So everybody had like different ways
of proving how it was, how it was a fraud. So there
was this one Rabbi, the רוגאטשובר, Rogatchover, who was known for his
like extremely encyclopedic knowledge of everything, and he said no, he knew
it was a fraud. Why? Because he said, in every מסכתא masechta
in ש"ס, Shas, you have one אמורא Amora who exists there that
doesn't exist anywhere in any other מסכתא. masechta. And here you don't
have it. So for him that was
a proof that it was a fraud.
Okay, but anyway there definitely is different distributions of the אמוראים. Amoraim.
So let's take a look at this issue, if it was lacking
between the קמיצה kmitza and the הקטרה. haktara. So איתמר, itmar, שיריים
שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה. shirayim shechasru bein kmitza lehaktara. You took the
קמיצה kmitza and you haven't burned it yet and then some of
the remnant was lacking. So רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer, מקטיר
קומץ עליהן, maktir kometz aleihen, you can still offer up the קומץ.
kometz. ריש לקיש אומר, Reish Lakish omer, אין מקטיר קומץ עליהן, ein
maktir kometz aleihen, you cannot. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אליבא דרבי אליעזר כולי עלמא לא פליגי. aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer kulei alma
lo pligi. They don't argue according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. You
might remember, Michael might remember, that there was a debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua back in זבחים Zevachim
of what happens if you no longer have the meat and the
fat of the קרבן, korban, can you still sprinkle the blood? Even
though the blood, the עבודה avoda of the blood is all you
need to be כשר, kasher, do you need there to be some
other part of the קרבן korban for the blood to validate? So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, no, even if there's no meat and
there's no fat and all you have left is the blood, sprinkle
it. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said, no, no, you need there
to be meat and fat in order to do some of the
sprinkling. Okay, so אליבא דרבי אליעזר, aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer, according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that כולי עלמא kulei alma
where am I, אליבא דרבי
אליעזר כולי עלמא לא פליגי,
aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer kulei
alma
lo pligi, that it's certainly כשר kasher because he would say by
animal קרבנות korbanos as well you don't need any remnant. כי פליגי
אליבא דרבי יהושע, ki pligi aliba de'Rabbi Yehoshua, they argue according to
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that said by animals it's no good.
דתנן, detnan, and here's the משנה: mishna: נטמאו שיריה nitmou sheyareiha if
the remnant was... and this is going to be... we're going to
see this later on by a מנחה. mincha. If the remnant became
טמא, tamei, נשרפו שיריה nisrefu sheyareiha or the remnant was burnt by
a מנחה, mincha, אבדו שיריה avdu sheyareiha or it was lost, כמידת
רבי אליעזר, kimidas Rabbi Eliezer, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says by a קרבן korban an animal קרבן korban you don't need
the meat and the fat, כשרה, kshaira, so this would be כשר.
kasher. Same analogy, you don't have the remnant of the מנחה mincha
but you can still offer up the handbreadth.
כמידת רבי יהושע, kimidas Rabbi Yehoshua, according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
פסולה, psula, it's invalid. So the exact debate by קרבן korban is
the debate by מנחה mincha in this case. So why is this
case different? So the גמרא Gemara will say: So it's obvious, yeah
it's obvious. מאן דפסל, man de'pasal, if you say it's invalid, כרבי
יהושע, ke'Rabbi Yehoshua, he's going like רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. If you're
missing the remnant, there's nothing left, it's invalid. ומן דמכשיר, u'man de'machshir,
but the one who says it's כשר kasher says one minute, עד
כאן לא אמר רבי יהושע התם אלא דלא אישתייר. ad kan lo
amar Rabbi Yehoshua hasam ela delo ishtayir. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says
it's invalid when nothing is left over. Then you can't do זריקת
הדם, zrikas hadam, then you can't do the קמיצה. kmitza. Here a
little is lost but most is left over. אבל הכא דאישתייר, aval
hacha de'ishtayir, here where something is left over, אפילו רבי יהושע מודה
ליה, afilu Rabbi Yehoshua modeh leh, even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would
agree. דתניא, detanya, and we have
a
ברייתא, braisa, רבי יהושע... Rabbi Yehoshua... one olive's worth of fat or
of meat is left over, you can do זורק הדם, zorik hadam,
you only need a little bit to do the זריקה. zrika. However,
if it's כחצי זית בשר כחצי זית חלב, kechatzi zayis basar kechatzi
zayis cheilev, if it's a half of a כזית kezayis of each,
אינו זורק את הדם, eino zoreik es hadam, you cannot sprinkle the
blood because those are different things: the meat is for eating and
the fat is for burning. However, ובעולה, uveolah, if you're talking with
a קרבן עולה, korban olah, אפילו כחצי זית בשר כחצי זית חלב
זורק את הדם. afilu kechatzi zayis basar kechatzi zayis cheilev zoreik es
hadam. Those two can combine because the meat and the fat are
both for burning. So therefore, even a half of a כזית kezayis
of meat and a half a כזית kezayis of fat, you can
go ahead and do זריקת הדם zrikat hadam because you have a
כזית, kezayis, a full כזית kezayis left of something to put on
the מזבח. mizbeach. Anyway, what do we see? We see that according
to Rabbi Yehoshua, one כזית kezayis is enough. So it's a good
question: why would you need the entire remnant of the מנחה mincha
in order to burn the קומץ? kometz? So מפני, mipnei, so first
finish the point of the עולה, olah, מפני שבעולה כולה כליל, mipnei
shebeolah kulla kalil, it's all burned. ובמנחה אף על פי שכולה קיימת
לא יזרוק. uvimincha af al pi shekullah kayemes lo yizrok. So now
this ברייתא braisa tells you that, well, let's take a look. First
it seems relevant, but then it doesn't make sense. Even if it's
all around, you can't זורק. zoreik. Now what do you mean זורק
zoreik by a מנחה? mincha? You burn the קומץ, kometz, it's not
זורק zoreik the blood. So the גמרא gemara says: ומנחה מאי עבידתא?
umincha mai avidta? What the heck is a מנחה mincha doing talking
about being זורק zoreik the blood? So אמר רב פפא: amar Rav
Pappa: no, here's what we mean, מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim. That if
all of the קרבן korban got lost but you have the מנחה
mincha that comes with the קרבן korban left, you can't say, oh,
that's part of the קרבן, korban, I can still do זריקת הדם,
zrikat hadam, because that's only, that's secondary, the primary קרבן korban is
completely lost. Okay, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would have
thought, הואיל ובהדי זבח אתיא, hoil uvahadei zevach asya, since it comes
with the animal, כגופא דזבח דמיא, kegufeh dizevach damya, it's like the
animal itself, קמשמע לן kamashma lan it's not and you can't do
זריקת הדם zrikat hadam if all you have left is the מנחת
נסכים minchas nesachim that came with the קרבן. korban. Now we have
a very good question: here we see that Rabbi Yehoshua says all
you need is a כזית. kezayis. So why by the מנחה mincha
would anybody say you need it to be entirely there? So
ומאן דפסל, uman dephasal, so the one that says it's invalid by
מנחה mincha even if a little is lacking would tell you שאני
הכא, shani hacha, here it's different, אמר קרא, amar kra, וירים הכהן
מן המנחה את אזכרתה והקטיר המזבחה. vayarim hakohen min hamincha es azkarasah
vehiktir hamizbeachah. The כהן kohen shall take from the מנחה mincha the
memory, meaning the thing to be remembered, the קומץ, kometz, and put
it on the מזבח. mizbeach. So we're going to say המנחה, hamincha,
עד דאיכא כולה מנחה לא יקטיר. ad deika kulla mincha lo yaktir.
So read the whole פסוק pasuk as one thing. We all, everybody
agrees the whole מנחה mincha has to be there when you take
the קומץ, kometz, agrees that the word המנחה hamincha means the מנחה
mincha has to be whole, but he's reading it, you take it
from the מנחה mincha והקטיר, vehiktir, even at the moment of הקטרה,
haktara, the מנחה mincha has to be whole. So really it has
nothing to do with Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua, even though the
normal סברא svara would say a כזית, kezayis, that you need only
a כזית kezayis left. Here the פסוק pasuk tells you you need
the whole מנחה mincha there when you do the
הקטרה. haktara. ואידך, veidach, what would the other one answer back? No,
מן המנחה min hamincha means מנחה שהיתה כבר, mincha shehayesa kvar, it
means it was a whole מנחה mincha when you took the קומץ,
kometz, but it does not have to be whole now when you
offer it up. Okay, so therefore what we're really saying is it's
not analogous to the קרבן, korban, it's based on a question of
do you have a special פסוק pasuk by the מנחה. mincha. איתיבי,
eiseivei, we're going to go see if we can get to the
two dots. איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. eiseivei Rabbi Yochanan lReish Lakish.
So we're now about ten lines down, the little ד daled in
brackets. איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, eiseivei Rabbi Yochanan lReish Lakish, so
Rabbi Yochanan challenged Reish Lakish. By the bread, we say what do
we say by the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? עד שלא פרקה נפרס
לחמה. ad shelo parkah nifras lachmah. If before you've removed the bread
from the table and the frankincense from the table, which is like
the קמיצה, kmitza, the bread broke, then הלחם פסול, halechem pasul, then
it's invalid. That's like the מנחה mincha that was invalid that got
lacking before you took the קמיצה. kmitza. ואין מקטיר עליה את הבזיכין,
ve-ein maktir aleha es habazichin, you don't offer up the cups of
frankincense. ואם משפרקה נפרס לחמה, ve-im misheparkah nifras lachmah, but if however
it broke after you removed it from the table and after you
took the בזיכין, bazichin, which is like it broke after the קמיצה,
kmitza, what's the הלכה? halacha? הלחם פסול, halechem pasul, the bread is
true, it is invalid. You cannot eat the remnant if that was
not whole. תוספות Tosfos discusses how we know that, but everybody agrees
you don't eat the remnant, ומקטיר עליה את הבזיכין, umaktir aleha es
habazichin, you can still offer up the little spoons of frankincense. So
that's like you can still offer up the קומץ. kometz. So here
it's explicit: some was lacking and you can still offer the קומץ
kometz up as long as it happened after the קומץ kometz was
taken. ואמר רבי אלעזר, veamar Rabbi Elazar, now this is completely irrelevant
to his proof, it's just the end of the quote. Rabbi Elazar
says: לא פרקה ממש, lo parkah mamash, it does not literally mean
that you've removed the frankincense, אלא כיון שהגיע זמנה לפרק, ela kivan
shehigia zmanah lefareik, when the time came to remove it, אף על
פי שלא פירקה, af al pi shelo pirkah, even if you haven't
removed it, it still counts like you've removed it. Okay, that was
parenthetical. But what do you see? Once you've removed the frankincense, then
if it breaks away the bread, you can still offer up the
frankincense. Once you take the קומץ, kometz, you should still be able
to offer it up.
If the bread breaks before, you wouldn't have the frankincense offering all
week? Correct.
Is that where we get the idea of a חלה challah on
שבת? Shabbos?
No.
Maybe you could say that metaphorically, but that's not where it comes
from. Anyways, גמרא Gemara says, so what does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
say back? אמר ליה המני רבי אליעזר היא. Amar lei hamani Rabbi
Eliezer hi. No, that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that even
by animal sacrifices you don't need anything leftover.
No, but the end is אמר רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, the
beginning is... what?
No, that was רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, the אמורא Amora blamed that.
Okay, this is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
who even by animal sacrifices doesn't need anything leftover. Our debate is
within an opinion that you need something leftover, whether you need the
whole amount leftover or not, whether a מנחה mincha requires more. But
that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that doesn't need anything leftover. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was offended. אנא אמינא
לך משנה שלמה, Ana amina lach mishna shleima, I've given you this
entire משנה. mishna. ואמרת לי את רבי אליעזר? v'amart li at Rabbi
Eliezer? You're telling me it's all רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? Now big
deal, we often do that, we say it's an individual opinion. But
here's why it's not a good read. אי רבי אליעזר מאי איריא
נפחת אפילו נשרף ואבד נמי מכשיר. Ei Rabbi Eliezer mai irya nifchat
afillu nisraf v'avad nami machshir. So why did רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
if it's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, why does it give the example
that a little piece broke off? Tell me a bigger חידוש, chiddush,
even if all of the bread was destroyed, right? That or even
if it was all burnt, it was all טמא. tamei. If it's
really רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says I don't care what happens
to any of the remnant. So אשתק, ishtik, he didn't have an
answer, he was silent. So ובמאי שתק, uv'mai shatak, the גמרא Gemara
says why was he silent? לימא ליה ציבור שאני, leima lei tzibbur
shani, why didn't he say "Oh, maybe there are different הלכות halachot
about a קרבן ציבור"? korban tzibbur Right, the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
is a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. So maybe a קרבן ציבור korban
tzibbur we would offer up the frankincense even if by an individual
קרבן korban we would not. ואמאי שתק, v'amai shatak, and why should
it be different?
דאפילו ציבור שאני הוא דאישתרי מטומאה לגביהו אישתרי נמי מחסרון. de'afillu tzibbur
shani hu de'ishtarei mitumah legabeihu ishtarei nami mechesron. Since by ציבור tzibbur
we overwrite טומאה, tumah, maybe we can overwrite other problems. Now we've
never heard that. For us it's always been טומאה tumah is overwritten
by a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, but that doesn't apply to other
things. But the גמרא Gemara is saying well if you're in a
corner maybe he could have said that, could have said "Ah, there
we go easier on you it's a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur and
you're allowed to do it." So אמר רב אדא בר אהבה זאת
אומרת, amar Rav Adda bar Ahava zos omeres, since he did not
give this answer this tells us החיסרון כבעל מום דמי ואין בעל
מום בציבור. hachisaron ke'ba'al mum dami v'ein ba'al mum b'tzibbur. It's not
like טומאה, tumah, it's like it's got a מום, mum, it's a
blemish, because literally something is missing. And the same way we don't
allow a בעל מום ba'al mum by a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur
we would not allow this. Now it is not literally like a
בעל מום. ba'al mum. If it was like a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, then it, then even if it was
חסר chaser after you took the קמיצה, kmitza, you would not be
able to offer up the קמיצה, kmitza, right? Even if it was
חסר chaser after the קמיצה kmitza was offered up you wouldn't or
whatever because you know a בעל מום ba'al mum is a בעל
מום, ba'al mum, you have to... you can never use a בעל
מום. ba'al mum. But what it means here is, is that it's
not like טומאה. tumah. It's like everything that is not טומאה tumah
that we never overwrite by a ציבור. tzibbur. The only thing we
overwrite by a ציבור tzibbur is טומאה, tumah, nothing
else. And therefore he could not say ציבור tzibbur is different because
the difference of ציבור tzibbur only exists by טומאה. tumah.
So right now we even... even according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
then you would still do it. That's what the conclusion is, right?
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has proven that, but the גמרא Gemara is
not done, so we will continue this tomorrow. But at this stage
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has proven that even according to רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua that normally requires a כזית, kezayit, right, that it's true,
by a מנחה mincha as well you would require a כזית, kezayit,
but not what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is arguing that you required
all to be there, because by the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim we
say that even if a little is lacking you can go ahead.
And that seems to prove again like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that
by a מנחה mincha you do not need all of it to
be there. So we'll finish with this tomorrow.
Have a great day.